Princetoniana Committee Oral History Project Records, 1994-2015: Preliminary Finding Aid AC259
University Archives
- Series 2: Princetoniana Committee Oral History Interviews, 1977-2015 May 12; 3 boxes
  - Harold Kuhn *1950, Part I, 2011 June 8; 1 box (Box 3)
    Kuhn discusses the G.I. Bill; researching with Professor Lefschetz; support from the Office of Naval Research and National Science Foundation; publishing in the Quarterly Journal of the Office of Naval Research; the development of the linear programming and operations research and financial engineering programs; the relationship between Princeton and the Institute for Advanced Studies; the math department's shift from topology to analytic number theory and algebra; and Nash's Nobel Prize nomination and his close relationship with Nash. He mentions classmates David Gale, Serge Lang, and Gino Calabi; Professors Lefschetz, Bochner, Nash, and Alan Tucker; Economics Department Chairman Dick Quant; Fine Hall Secretary Agnes Henry; Mathematics Department Associate Hale Trotter; and faculty Chevalley and Wigner.
  - Harold Kuhn *1950, Part II, 2011 June 15; 1 box (Box 3)
    In the second part of his interview, Kuhn talks about the low quality of the Kelley committee papers; the Vietnam assembly; being a member of the advisory committee on policy to the President; shaping University policy regarding student record confidentiality; the May 1968 student demonstration on confidentiality; presentations for the Advisory Committee in 1968; the Kelley committee; having students present during faculty meetings; student committee implementation for academic departments; working on the development of "Students and the University"; the Committee on Committees; the poor state of committee rules and University regulations; the development of CPUC; the occupation of New South by the Association of Black Colleagues; and ROTC. He mentions Professor Stuart Hampshire, Trustee John Doar, and Chairman of the Physics Department Bob Dickey.
  - Yeiichi (Kelly) Kuwayama '40, 2011 December 21; 1 box (Box 3)
    Yeiichi "Kelly" Kuwayama, Class of 1940, helped establish a diversity fund for Princeton and attended Harvard Business School.
    In his interview, Kuwayama discusses growing up in New York City; Princeton's lack of diversity; bicker as singling out poor students; challenges faced by poor students; living in Edwards, Witherspoon, and Dod; dorm costs; working in New York on the weekends; being discriminated against for his Asian ethnicity on campus and on Wall Street; Princeton's diversification since his graduation; the diminishing prominence of the eating clubs; divisions within the Asian community along national lines; A4P (Asians for Princeton); precepts; fighting for the U.S. instead of Japan in World War II; and Harvard's more accepting environment. He mentions Professors Graham, Oppenheimer, and Reschauer and President Dodds.
  - Oliver Langenberg '35, 2008 February 8; 1 box (Box 3)
    Oliver Langeberg, Class of 1935, majored in Philosophy.
    Langeberg talks about attending St. Paul's School; not being allowed to drive at Princeton; Renwick's restaurant; his membership in Cap and Gown; living in 49 dorm; bedbug issues; playing bridge; being drafted in 1941; working for a brokerage firm, Gaylord Container, and A.G. Edwards; President Tilghman's personality; raising money for his class; and Professor Gauss.
  - Maurice Lee '46, 2011 June 18; 1 box (Box 3)
    Maurice Lee, Class of 1945, majored in History and returned to Princeton in 1946 as a Woodrow Wilson Fellow, becoming an assistant professor in 1953.
    Lee speaks about growing up in Greenwich; attending Hotchkiss; living in Lower Pyne, Joline, and Holder; the V7 military program closing some dorms; President Dodd's underwhelming presence; the presidential election of 1944; not having bicker or a football team because of the war; the lack of enforcement of the drinking age; serving in the Navy; the GI Bill; the reaction to the first woman, Suzanne Keller, being hired at Princeton; and the History Department graduate council. He mentions History Department Head Joe Strayer, staff member Jinks Harbison, Ira Wade of the French Department, librarian Bill Dix, and Dean of the College Christian Gauss.
  - Vera Marcus '72, Part I, 2012 March; 1 box (Box 3)
    Vera Marcus, Class of 1972, majored in Philosophy. She is a member of the first graduating female class admitted as freshmen and the first African American to attend Princeton from freshman year and graduate. She attended University of California at Davis Martin Luther King School of Law.
    In the transcript, Marcus describes her childhood in Birmingham during the Civil Rights Movement; her isolating experience being a part of one of the first integrated classes at West End High School; her sister being one of the first black students admitted to an all-white school; Martin Luther King visiting her family; being the head of State Wild and Scenic Rivers Task Force for California; living in Pyne Hall; busses of girls coming into Princeton during weekends; being recruited by Princeton; and Theater Intime.
  - Vera Marcus '72, Part II, 2012 April; 1 box (Box 3)
    In the second part of her interview, Marcus mentions her friend and classmate Dianna Toliver, from Trinidad; the lack of diversity in friend groups at Princeton; the divisions at Princeton being strong along gender lines than racial ones; participating in Harambee House Theater; travelling with Triangle Club; facing exclusion from social life as a black woman; and not being allowed into eating clubs.
  - Henry Martin '48, 2010 June 19; 1 box (Box 3)
    Henry Martin, Class of 1948, was an Art History major and has published cartoons in The New Yorker.
    Martin talks about growing up in Louisville; drawing cartoons for Tiger Magazine and helping to restart the magazine after the war; attending Rugby, Woodbury Forest, and Texas Country Day School where he graduated from in 1944; living in Witherspoon, Pyne, and Patton; attending commercial art school in Chicago; writing his thesis on the history of cartoons; and contribution to the 100th anniversary edition of Tiger Magazine. He mentions Henry Toll, '42, Bernie Peyton, '49, and Professor Stohlman.
  - James McPherson, 2012 May 30; 1 box (Box 3)
    James McPherson is the David Emeritus Professor of History. He came to Princeton in 1962 and was promoted to assistant professor in 1965. He wrote Battle Cry of Freedom.
    McPherson discusses graduates teaching as assistant instructors in the 1960s; senior faculty teaching precepts; the popularity of seminar style classes; teaching in the American Studies interdepartmental program; the Kent State shooting; student demonstrations against the Institute for Defense Analysis; the History Department's effort to diversify; coeducation; the Civil Rights Movement; the internet and amateur historians; and the Princeton History Department compared to other History Departments.
  - Mary Nelson '77, 2009 October 8; 1 box (Box 3)
    Mary Nelson, Class of 1966, was one of the first black women to attend Princeton. She attended University of Missouri at Columbia Law School. She also worked for the Speaker of the Missouri House of Representatives as Legislative Director and General Counsel.
    Nelson played varsity basketball freshman year and varsity volleyball throughout her time at Princeton. In her interview, she discusses growing up in St. Louis; men treating women poorly at Princeton; the poor quality of women's sports facilities and equipment; professors being obstinate to women taking part in discussions; one professor telling insulting limericks about females in Latin; learning from Cornel West; living in Holder and Spelman; eating in Commons; working at the Student Center; black students not being able to go to eating clubs; limited social participation for black women; the nude Olympics; and coed bathrooms. She mentions staff member Marguerite Ross Bernett, and Professor Howard Taylor.
  - Lee Neuwirth '55 and James Tarlau '70, 2013 September 6; 1 box (Box 4)
    Lee Neuwirth, Class of 1955, was Chairman of his class's 25th Reunion. James Tarlau, Class of 1970.
    Neuwirth talks about coeducation; black students; Vietnam War protests; being one of a few Jewish students; bicker; his membership in Elm Club; Ivy Club's popularity; most clubs being unaccepting of Jewish students; Princeton's atmosphere of privilege and arrogance; the Association of Black Collegians; President Goheen; challenges faced by activists at Princeton; demonstrating to let women into Cottage Club; Cottage Club evading tax payments; the elimination of the chapel requirement; and the requirement of permission from the Dean to marry during undergraduate years. Tarlau discusses growing up in New York City; being one of the most radical liberals at Princeton; the lack of a liberal student group on campus; Confederate Flags in student rooms; Princeton being like a "southern prep school" and elitist; little social change movement on campus; putting up pictures of napalmed babies around campus; being arrested for possession of heroin after college; community organizing; hoping to break the relationship between Princeton and the government; seeking to hinder war efforts; wanting to weaken the Institute for Defense Analyses; the relationship between white and black Princeton activists; challenges faced by Princeton activists; travelling to rallies and protests while at school; activism's evolution at Princeton; the underground newspaper Prism; and Whig Clio.
  - Carol Obertubbesing '73, 2008 May 30; 1 box (Box 3)
    Carol Obertubbesing, Class of 1973, majored in History and was one of the first one hundred women at Princeton. ¬¬She made her career in public TV and radio, is involved in the Princeton Club of Chicago, and is a Project 55 mentor.
    In her interview, Obertubbesing discusses growing up in Union City; living in Pyne Hall; the women's dorms' special security systems; limited socializing for women; the challenges of not coming from a private school; women singled out in classes by professors; being a woman and participating in classes; being asked by men how to do laundry; men feeling resentment towards women; being a social member of Colonial Club; the 1 to 7 grading system; no physical education requirement for women; sports; eating in Commons; terrible food quality; parties at Colonial Club; the Aquinas Institute; dating; women and eating clubs; clothing style; changes in society affecting Princeton; the student strike of 1970; the primarily black theater in New Brunswick; writing her thesis on women in American film. She mentions classmates Georgia Nugent, Margie Gengler-Smith, and Robin Herman.
  - Lydia Osborne h50 h74 h83, 2012 October 24; 1 box (Box 3)
    Lydia Osborne is an honorary member of classes of 1950, 1974, and 1983. She is a longstanding member of the staff of Princeton Alumni Council and served as the Assistant to the Director of the Alumni Council.
    Osborne discusses: her father's role as Director of Public Relations and Assistant Secretary of Princeton; that she graduated from Princeton High school in 1965; her father was editor of Princeton Herald; provided events for alumni, planned reunions and Alumni Day, worked with class officers; was Assistant to the Director of the Alumni Council; staff liaison; relationship between Alumni Council and Administration; Princeton Journeys Program; travelling with Alumni Council; participation on Princeton Journeys trips; attending football games; student strike of 1970 and Administration's reaction; worried about coeducation; lack of contact between Alumni Council and eating clubs; tailgate at Jadwin; Ivy Plus conference; HYPD Alumni Councils directors meeting; diversification; relationship between Alumni Council and Annual Giving; uproar over coeducation; and alumni community. Mentions directors of alumni council Dan White, Dave Rahr, Charlie Taggart, and Kathy Taylor; Freddie Fox,;President Dodds; alum Jimmy Stewart; Admiral Crowe; General Petraeus; and Senator Bill Frist '74; Bob Rogers '56.
  - Charles R. Parmele III '47, 2011 June 18; 1 box (Box 3)
    Charles R. Parmele III, Class of 1947, was a Woodrow Wilson School History major and graduated with honors. He was the treasure of the class of 1947 and ran annual giving and Memorial Insurance for Princeton. He started Parmele, McDermott and Thomas Insurance Company.
    Parmele was a varsity tennis recruit at Princeton. He went into the Army at Fort Benning and Fort Dix in 1943 and graduated late in 1949 and was assistant sergeant major at Midpack. Many of his classmates were killed in the war. In his interview, he mentions wealthy but unintelligent students; lessening course requirements; the relationship between undergrads and professors; researching Woodrow Wilson; his membership in Tiger Inn; reunions; the Garibaldi lecture; wearing Army clothing and the political mood on campus; the treatment of Jewish students; the lack of black students; Einstein being a ladies man; the social life only being good for wealthy students; and becoming the ping pong champion of the university senior year. He mentions the Murray-Dodge family, Professor Eric Goldman, Dean Mathey, squash coach Bob Callahan, class president Mark Baldwin, Professor Buzzer Hall, President Dodds.
  - Robin Pearse-Drance '73, 2014 June 21; 1 box (Box 4)
    Robin Pearse-Drance, Class of 1973, majored in Art History and attended Bennett College before transferring to Princeton.
    Pearse-Drance talks about attending Miss Porter's School; working for the Movement for a New Congress; being a former "import" girl, coming to Princeton on the weekends; marijuana on campus; "import" girls being "cute but dumb"; the Dean Reynolds's take on women at Princeton; male treatment of females; playing football; Triangle Club; being the only girl in a navigation class; Princeton being a "white man's world"; getting tapped by Cap and Gown, and Quad, but joining Quad; women's clothing; attending seminary; and owning an interior design business. She mentions Joan Gallos '73.
  - Theodore K. Rabb *61, 2009 September 17; 1 box (Box 3)
    Theodore K. Rabb received his Ph.D. from Princeton in 1960 after studying at Oxford. He is a Professor Emeritus of History at Princeton. He was an assistant professor at Harvard and a professor at Stanford and Northwestern. He was also Chairman of the American Historical Association's Committee on Quantitative History and is responsible for helping create the "HUM Sequence." He helped create the PBS series Renaissance, which aired in 1993, and was nominated for an Emmy. He is featured in Who's Who 2008 edition.
    In the transcript, Rabb talks about education at Oxford versus in America; living in Butler Tract; campus cost of living; the grad school community; Princeton's History Department; the historical demography field; the Journal of Interdisciplinary History; bureaucratic hurdles in creating the "HUM Sequence"; and building the community college internship program. He mentions Columbia professor Garrett Mattingly; Princeton professors E. H. Harbison, Frank Craven, and Elmer Beller; Chairmen of the History Department Jerry Blum and Joseph Strayer, historian Lewis Spitz, and Regius Professor Hugh Trevor-Roper.
  - Robert H. Rawson, Jr. '66, 2007 June 2; 1 box (Box 3)
    Robert H. Rawson, Jr., Class of 1966, majored in the Woodrow Wilson School, and was president of his class during his senior year. He won the Rhodes Scholarship in 1966. He served 20 years as a trustee and 13 as Chair of the Executive Committee.
    Rawson describes growing up in Shaker Heights and attending Shaker Heights High School; working for the USG staff; working with President Goheen; Bill Bradley and the basketball team going to the "Final Four" in 1965; the 1965 undefeated football season; and searching for a president for Princeton and selecting Shirley Tilghmann. His wife was the Shaker Heights Mayor. He mentions visiting Professor Reinhold Neibuhr, Professor Bill Bowen, Assistant Professor and his thesis advisor John Strange, and Jim Baker '52.
  - David Reeves '48, 2011 June 18; 1 box (Box 3)
    David Reeves, Class of 1948, served as the Class of 1948 Secretary for 38 years. He went to the Army Air Force before attending college. He helped set up the AA Haven at Reunions.
    Reeves grew up in Baltimore, attending several Princeton football games, and recalls watching fullback w. Pepper-Constable. He talks about living in 1903 Hall, Nassau Club, and an apartment in Palmer Square; the GI Bill; Woodrow Wilson; the changes of coeducation and more minority students, especially Asian and students; Princeton's elitist atmosphere; being a member in and on the board of Colonial Club; bicker; discussing closing Colonial down; eating clubs; the construction of Corwin Hall and Firestone Library; and the campus expansion plan. He mentions advisor Shorty McCabe; classmates Bill Merwin, Galway Kinnel, and Bob Heiman; Dean and High-Church Episcopalian Aldridge; Professors Jerry Blum, Jinks Harbison, Ted Mommsen, Buzzer Hall, and Joe Strayer; Presidents Dodds and Goheen; his father's classmates Edgar Palmer and Moses Taylor Pyne; Princeton's first ordained rabbi Joel Dobin; Freddie Fox '39; Bill Bowen; Jimmy Griffin; and Alum and President of Kenyon College Georgia Nugent.
  - Harvey Rothberg '49, 2011; 1 box (Box 3)
    Harvey Rothberg, Class of 1949, majored in Biology. He attended Harvard Medical School, went into the Army for three years, did research at Walter Reed Army Medical Center, and taught medical school in New Jersey.
    In his interview, Rothberg speaks about V-J Day; the difficulty of graduating on time; a graduation ceremony in Alexander Hall; summer sessions; being Jewish at Princeton; being told by his Yale interviewer that Jewish students didn't have social lives; eating in Commons; eating clubs not taking Jewish students; not socializing with other Jewish students; joining Prospect Cooperative Club; Jewish classmates leaving Princeton; living in Dod Hall, Pyne Hall, and Henry Hall; being premed; compulsory chapel attendance; the small synagogue on Spring Street; alternative Jewish services; Jewish services in Murray-Dodge; Protestant chapel speakers; his Reform Jewish background; Humanities 252, the Western Tradition taught by E. Harris Harbison; Shakespeare 101; taking the train to Times Square to celebrate the end of the war; President Dodds and Goheen; coeducation; Architecture Department Head Bob Geddes; reunions; Princeton's science programs; Shirley Tlighman; and a Graphic Arts Seminar by Elmer Adler.
  - Neil Rudenstine '56, 2009; 1 box (Box 3)
    Neil Rudenstine, Class of 1956, won the Rhodes Scholarship and studied Modern History and English at Oxford. He served as an assistant professor, Dean of Students, and Provost at Princeton. He worked for Princeton's Mellon Foundation, and became the "Working Chair" on the Foundation's ARTstor project. He also received his Ph.D. from Harvard where he worked for the English Department. He eventually became the President of Harvard.
    Rudenstine discusses growing up in Danburry; Princeton's social atmosphere; the Special Program in the Humanities; playing bridge; being a member of Quadrangle Club; being deferred by the Army after winning the Rhodes; dealing with the Vietnam War, South African investments, coeducation, and the minority, women, and war movements while Dean of Students; diversifying the Dean of Students's staff; challenges faced as Provost, including with the University budget and preventing deficits; creating Princeton's molecular biology, computer science, and creative arts programs; making graduate work the focus of the Mellon Foundation; restructuring Harvard's administration, the "Mind, Brain, and Behavior" program, creating the Asian Center, bringing the Humanities departments together, and the construction of Annenberg Hall. He mentions his mother's Italian immigrant family; his father's Russian Jewish background; alum John Verdery; classmates Jim Market, Peter McDavitt, Coleman Brown, Royce Flippin, and Bob Post; Professors Bowen, Harbison, and Alba Warren; Assitant Deans Joe Moore, Halcy Bohen, and Carl Fields; Princeton President Goheen; Harvard President Bok; and Aaron Lemonick.
  - William Scheide '36, 2007 June 1; 1 box (Box 4)
    William Scheide, Class of 1936, studied history and is part of the Scheide family connected to the Scheide Library in Titusville. He received an M.A. in music from Columbia in 1940.
    This is an interview with William "Bill" Scheide. He is accompanied by his wife Judy Scheide and Eric Shultz who assist him in the interview. In the transcript, Scheide describes his family's library and its changes in content, location, and ownership within the family throughout the years; his love of Bach and eventual involvement in Bach Atria; learning piano and adding music to the family library; starting the Music Department at Princeton with Ralph Downs and Professor Roy Welch; his friends at Princeton leaving to pursue music elsewhere; Professor "Buzzer" Hall and Preceptor Lynn White from Princeton; meeting his wife at Princeton who read his thesis at Mudd; his grandfather and his purchase of a Bible manuscript; meeting and interacting with John D. Rockefeller Jr. and Chief Justice Earl Warren; his association with the NAACP Legal Defense Fund and joining the Civil Rights Committee at Princeton; walking into a lecture by Einstein in McCosh 50; and being a member of Terrace Club.
  - Lisa W. Schmucki '74, 2014; 1 box (Box 4)
    Lisa Schmucki, Class of 1974, majored in History. Her father was Class of 1941 and president of his class, and her daughter was Class of 2007.
    In her interview, Lisa Schmucki discusses attending Kent Place Girls' Day School; paying for her Princeton education; living in Princeton Inn, Patton, and Henry; the residential college system and the nearly 50/50 gender balance within them; the construction of the Forbes College Addition; the Princeton Inn being the place for the most liberal students, a "hippie haven," and a "drug haven"; a religion professor's weekly night lectures in the Princeton Inn during which all of the students smoked marijuana; graduate student RAs; going to protests in Trenton; most of her gender-based restrictions being self-imposed; Professor Nancy Malkiel; no one reaching out to or looking out for specifically female students; a feeling of socio economic equality on campus; room parties; The Pub in Chancellor Green where you could buy alcohol with your student card; playing Pong the video game and a jukebox in The Pub; the fancy and sophisticated atmosphere at the eating clubs; 20-minute interviews with eating club members for bicker; bicker being good for women since there weren't many on campus; membership in Cap and Gown Club; "import" girls; limited non-varsity sports options; being in the Tigerlilies A capella group and Glee Club; traveling to South America with the Glee Club and Smith College Chorus; being popular as one of the first Princeton "coeds"; Emily Goodfellow Class of 1976; going into accounting after college at Arthur Andersen; being on the board of Cap and Gown Club and a GICC advisor to the eating clubs; and helping to orchestrate Truck Fest.
  - William Selden '34, 2006; 1 box (Box 4)
    William Selden, Class of 1934, majored in the Woodrow Wilson School.